Guide to the Blanche Espy Chenoweth Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Blanche Espy Chenoweth Papers
1875-1960
02/2005-003
Chenoweth, Blanche Espy
6.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Containing 13 series and housed in 6 boxes, this collection documents Mrs. Chenoweth's life's work as a lecturer and writer. Most notably, her lecture and radio show program materials are extensively represented in such formats as article clippings, correspondence, typescript, periodicals and photographic material.
Biographical Information:
Born in Scotch Grove, Iowa in 1875, Blanche Espy Chenoweth was a well respected lecturer and writer in her time. She was a student of Mary Baldwin College and the University of Chicago. She lived in places such as Chicago; Chautauqua, New York; and Tulsa, Oklahoma, but called Houston her home for the last 25 years of her life.
Mrs. Chenoweth gave countless lectures on women’s dress and grooming and their importance in a successful, happy life. In the late 1920s, she was a prominent lecturer and writer regarding the problems of women at the Chautauqua Institution. In 1930 she published a compilation of her lectures in a booklet entitled Clothes and Happiness. Throughout the 1930's she had a "personal problems" radio program in Chicago first called the Homemaking Hour which later became known as Little Dramas from Life. During her time in Chicago, she also wrote an advice-giving newspaper column.
In addition to lecturing, Mrs. Chenoweth was active in organizations such as the League of American Pen Women, the Daughters of the American Revolution, Association of University Women and was a life member of the Huguenot Society of South Carolina. She was also active in affairs of the Presbyterian Church.
Mrs. Chenoweth died in March of 1960 at the age of 85 after battling a long illness. She was survived by her one son Robert Carey Chenoweth and four grandchildren.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Articles; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Memorabilia; Periodicals; Photographs; Scripts (documents)
Personal Name:
Chenoweth, Blanche Espy
Topical Term:
Femininity; Lecturers
Separated Materials:
Blanche Espy Chenoweth Papers cataloged book collection (https://library.uh.edu/search~S11?/tBlanche+Espy+Chenoweth+Papers./tblanche+espy+chenoweth+papers/-3%2C-1%2C0%2CB/exact&FF=tblanche+espy+chenoweth+papers&1%2C15%2C)
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Related Materials:
Blanche Espy Chenoweth, Her Life, Her Times digital collection http://digital.lib.uh.edu/collection/cheno
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
Containing 13 series and housed in 6 boxes, this collection documents Mrs. Chenoweth's life's work as a lecturer and writer. Most notably, her lecture and radio show program materials are extensively represented in such formats as article clippings, correspondence, typescript, periodicals and photographic material. Mrs. Chenoweth's papers also document her social interactions with prominent individuals such as Queen Marie of Romania and President Herbert Hoover. Additionally, this collection contains important memorabilia Mrs. Chenoweth collected throughout her life and materials that document important family history information.
Detailed List of Contents
- Personal Correspondence
  - Mary Jane Carey Espy (mother) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daniel Austin Chenoweth (husband) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Robert Carey Chenoweth (son) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Acquaintances (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Regarding Employment Opportunities, 1915, 1932, 1933, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Regarding an Honorary Bachelor's Degree from The Teachers' College, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Social Interactions
  - Invitation and Program to Dinner Honoring Queen Marie, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Invitation from President Hoover to the Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Queen Marie's Obituary, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tribute to the Late Founder and President of The Teacher's College, 1926 (Ovs box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles regarding Roumanian Queen Marie's visit to Indianapolis, 1926 (Ovs box 3, Folder 2)
- Organizations
  - National League of American Pen Women Official Bulletins, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Huguenot Society of South Carolina - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Huguenot Society of South Carolina - Certificate (Ovs box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pin Collection - Huguenot Society of South Carolina pin (Ovs box 4, Item 1)
  - Pin Collection - College Sorority pin (Ovs box 4, Item 2)
  - Pin Collection - Daughters of American Revolution pin (Ovs box 4, Item 3)
  - Pin Collection - National League of American Pen Women pin (Ovs box 4, Item 4)
  - Pin Collection - Robert C. Chenoweth's Navy pin (Ovs box 4, Item 5)
- Educational Experience
  - Materials regarding her attendance at Mary Baldwin Seminary, the University of Chicago, Purdue University and Indiana University (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1927 Chautauqua Institution Program Assembly Photographs (Ovs box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Chautauquan Daily, 1926-1927 (Ovs box 3, Folder 5)
- Chicago World's Fair
  - Correspondence regarding being the hostess of the Indiana Building at the Chicago World's Fair, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Book of Comments from Chicago World's Fair Listeners, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lecture Materials
  - Notes, Correspondence, Invoices, and Other Lecture Materials
    - Correspondence regarding Lectures, 1926-1932, 1934, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Programs from Lecture Events, 1926-1932 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Invoices to and from L.S. Ayres and Company for Lectures Given, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lecture Notes and Charts (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lecture Notebooks (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Articles regarding Lectures, 1924-1930, 1932, undated (Ovs box 3, Folder 6)
  - Research
    - Pamphlets, 1925, 1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Articles, 1925-1928, 1930-1931, 1949, undated (Ovs box 3, Folder 7)
  - Materials related to Published Works
    - Copyright Papers and Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Clothes and Happiness Booklet: A Collection of Chenoweth's Lectures, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Clothes and Happiness Brochures and Printed Promotional Material (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Sketches for Booklet Cover Page (Ovs box 3, Folder 8)
- Radio Broadcast: Homemakers' Hour/Little Dramas from Life
  - Correspondence regarding Radio Broadcast, 1928-1936 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Radio Broadcast Notes, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Photograph of Chenoweth's First Broadcast (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Homemakers' Hour, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Little Dramas from Life, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Little Dramas from Life, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Little Dramas from Life, January–July 1934 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Little Dramas from Life, August–December 1934 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Broadcast Scripts and Correspondence - Little Dramas from Life, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Articles regarding Radio Broadcast, 1930-1931, 1933 (Ovs box 3, Folder 9)
  - Little Dramas From Life Glass Record and Script, 1940 (Ovs box 4, Item 6)
- Column Written by Blanche E. Chenoweth
  - As Mother Sees It, 1931 (Ovs box 3, Folder 10)
- Personal Milestones
  - Blanche E. Chenoweth’s Wedding Invitation (1898) and Funeral Register (1960), 1898, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Family History
  - Correspondence and Articles regarding Ancestry (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Scotch Grove Cemetery Materials and Burial Information (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mary A. Espy (paternal grandmother) Obituary (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Nancy Agnes Carey (maternal grandmother) Obituary (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Other Carey Family Obituaries (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Robert Johnston Espy (father) Service Discharge/Pension Papers, Marriage Certificate, and Burial Plot Purchase (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Robert Johnston Espy (father) Obituaries (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Mary Jane Carey Espy (mother) Correspondence with cousin George McKinstry (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Mary Jane Carey Espy (mother) Teaching Certificate and Letters from Old Students (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Mary Jane Carey Espy (mother) Death Certificate and Obituary (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Robert Carey Chenoweth (son) Birth Certificate and U.S. Navy Papers (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Robert Carey Chenoweth (son) Family History Essay and College Thesis (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "The Espy Family in America" by Florence Mercy Espy (aunt) (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Portion of Family History by Mary Jane Carey Espy (mother) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes regarding Family History (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Robert Johnston Espy (father) American and European Secret Service Certificate (Ovs box 3, Folder 11)
- Photographic Material
  - Photographs of Blanche E. Chenoweth (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Photographs of Robert J. Espy (father), Daniel A. Chenoweth (husband), and Grandmother Chenoweth (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Individual Photographs of Robert C. Chenoweth (son) and Photographs of Blanche and Son (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Chenoweth and Espy Family Houses (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Additional Family Photographs (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Shelbyville, Tennessee, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Colorado Trip, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Miami, Florida, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Deland, Florida, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - North Carolina, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Chautauqua Institution and the University of Chicago (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Photo Album (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Negatives (Box 2, Folder 63-64)
  - Large Portraits of Blanche E. Chenoweth (Ovs box 4, Folder 7)
  - Framed Portrait of Blanche E. Chenoweth (Ovs box 4, Item 8)
  - Framed Portraits of Blanche E. Chenoweth and Robert C. Chenoweth (Ovs box 4, Item 9)
  - Framed Portrait of Cecilius Calvert (ancestor) (Ovs box 4, Item 10)
- Collected Poetry
  - Writings and Article Clippings (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - The Ideal Scrapbook: Poem Collection (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Memorabilia
  - Religious Books and Pamphlets
    - Attractive Fruitbearing by Henry Durbanville (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Unfailing Promises from His Word by Presbyterian Church, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Historical Magazine Issues and Newspaper Sections
    - Indianapolis Daily Journal (1864) and the Washington Herald (1931), 1864, 1931 (Ovs box 3, Item 12)
    - The Woman's World Service Library: The Garden Book, 1932 (Ovs box 5, Item 1)
    - The Woman's World Service Library: The Patchwork Book, 1932 (Ovs box 5, Item 2)
    - LIFE, December 1, 1947 (Ovs box 5, Item 3)
    - LIFE (cover page only), February 18, 1952 (Ovs box 5, Item 4)
    - LIFE, February 2, 1953 (Ovs box 5, Item 5)
    - LIFE, April 27, 1953 (Ovs box 5, Item 6)
    - LIFE (cover page only), November 16, 1953 (Ovs box 5, Item 7)
    - The Illustrated London News, February 23, 1952 (Ovs box 5, Item 8)
    - The Illustrated London News, April 4, 1953 (Ovs box 5, Item 9)
    - The Illustrated London News, May 30, 1953 (Ovs box 5, Item 10)
    - The Illustrated London News, May 22, 1954 (Ovs box 5, Item 11)
    - The Saturday Evening POST, October 11, 1952 (Ovs box 5, Item 12)
    - Town and Country, August 1951 (Ovs box 5, Item 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Market Account Receipts, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Black Metal Strong Box (Box 2, Item 83)
    - Imperial King Edward the Seventh Empty Tobacco Box (Box 2, Item 84)
    - Empty Leather Document Portfolio (Box 2, Item 85)
    - China Tea Set Hand Painted by Blanche E. Chenoweth, 1893 (Ovs box 6, Item 1)
    - Copper Printing Plate (Ovs box 6, Item 2)
    - Silver Calling Card Holder (Ovs box 6, Item 3)
    - 1888 Quarter (Ovs box 6, Item 4)
    - Late 19th Century Evening Bags (Ovs box 6, Item 5)
    - Dress Sewn by Blanche E. Chenoweth, 1897 (Ovs box 7, Item 1)